FADDY MICHEL

JAVA SOFTWARE ENGINEER

faddy.michel@gmail.com / (347) 791-7348

I studied Computer Science for five years (2005-2010). Since then, I have been working as a software engineer in two big cities, Cairo and New York City. During this period, I gained very good experience in Software Houses, News & Media, E-Commerce utilizing solid technology stacks for producing high-traffic consumer-facing web applications. In each job, the challenge starts with self-learning and ends with mastering the systems and platforms that handles the majority of the work. These systems include Adobe CQ5/AEM, Demandware, Netsuite, AWS, GCP, Jenkins, Apache Maven, Java Collections Framework, Java NIO, Apache Lucene Core, etc. My experience also goes beyond the back-end side to the front-end side working with various technology stacks that are based on the three major web languages, HTML, CSS and Javascript. I have a very good understanding of the software production approaches being used in the market nowadays and the software tools, JIRA and Git mainly, for managing the different steps of the process.

Facts

llk means Low-Level Knowledge. hlk means High-Level Knowledge.

Programming: bash (llk), GNU coreutils (llk), C (hlk), Java (llk), JavaScript (llk), Python (hlk), awk (hlk), Perl (hlk), SQL (hlk), Csound (hlk), lilypond (llk), HTML (llk), CSS (llk), LaTeX (llk).

Platforms: Unix/Linux (llk), AWS (hlk), Adobe CQ/AEM (hlk), Demandware (hlk), NetSuite (hlk), MySQL (hlk), Apache Cassandra (hlk), MongoDB (hlk).

Operating Systems: GNU Linux/Debian (llk), MacOS (llk), Ubuntu (llk), Windows (hlk), Android (hlk), iOS (hlk), JoliOS (hlk), Chrome OS (hlk), Firefox OS (hlk).

Projects

OCT 2018--PRESENTSoftware Engineer of jed

Building Java EDiting tools to facilitate the process of coding from the commandline. It provides the "cls" command, which lists and searches the classpath for available classes. Currently, working on the "mbr" command which lists and searches the members of selected class or classes.

Employment History

AUG 2015--MAR 2016Senior Software Engineer at Poppin

At Poppin, there was three different technologystacks. Here s the work done within each stack:

- 1. NetSuite, Business Management Software, led the development of:
 - Re-engineering and putting down the architecture of the code-base.
 - Developing a new model for selecting warehouse locations for each sales order.

- Modifying and changing the data models for companies, contacts and customers, and the relationships between them, by writing a variety of scripts to migrate the current data.
- Writing a service responsible for exporting records and sublists as CSV.
- Bug fixing.
- 2. Demandware, E-commerce Platform, contributed to:
 - Re-designing Poppin's web application.
 - Modified the categorization model of products and making better use of the slicing attributes.
 - Bug fixing.
- 3. Scruffy, an In-house Java-based Feeds Management System, contributed to:
 - Refactoring customers feeds.
 - Bug fixing.

MAR 2015--MAY 2015Senior Software Engineer at PM Digital

Contributed to various projects for HP, ColorLok and KPMG. Focused on the front-end by helping adding and creating new UI modules and components. Technologies used include Adobe AEM/CQ, NodeJS, Grunt, AngularJS, Handlebars, SASS and LESS.

FEB 2015--JUL 2015Founder of Ballura

Java SE, Apache Cassandra, Apache Solr and Java Jersey.

 ${\tt JAN~2013--DEC~2014} Software~Engineer~at~The~Daily~Beast~/~Newsweek$

Adobe CQ5, Java SE, Apache Solr, JavaScript, JQuery, HTML, DustJS, CSS, Less and Google Analytics.

JAN 2011--NOV 2011**Junior Software Engineer at TekTrust**Java, Appian, PHP, Elgg, HTML, CSS, JavaScript and
JQuery.

AUG 2008--NOV 2008Intern Software Engineer at Atlantic Industries — The Cocacola Compa PHP, XML, Microsoft SQL, HTML, CSS and JavaScript.

Education

B.Sc., Computer Science and Engineering: 2005–2010 at German University in Cairo.